Guide to the Rose Schneiderman Papers TAM.018
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series I: Correspondence. (Reel 7099/113: Frames 1-914)
  - Subseries B: Correspondence 1915-1964. (Reel 7099/113: Frames 367-785)
    Correspondence in the second group, 1915-1964, is more diffuse and has more of the character of personal memorabilia. With three exceptions, each year is represented by no more than half a dozen items; some years are skipped altogether. The exceptions are large clusters of letters and telegrams sent on three occasions: in 1937, at the time of Schneiderman's appointment as New York State Secretary of Labor; in 1943, in observance of the twenty fifth anniversary of her presidency of the New York Women's Trade Union League; and in 1949, when she retired from that post. Corrpspondents in this portion of the reel include Margaret Dreier Robins (see esoecially June 24, 1922, June 14, 1943, and Schneiderman's reply of July 7, 1943), Mary Dreier, Leonora O'Reilly, Elisabeth Christman (including several letters in 1950 describing the closing down of the National WTUL headquarters), Frances Perkins, the English labor leader Margaret Bondfield, Franklin D. Roosevelt (several letters during his governorship), and Eleanor Roosevelt. On trade union affairs, Schneiderman in a letter of Feb. 6, 1916 to Benjamin Schlesinger submits her resignation as an ILGWU organizer. (See also her letter to Abe Baroff, Dec 1, 1916, on Reel 2, frames 262-263.) A letter from Max Zaritsky, June 7, 1934, announces her election to the general executive board of her own union, the United Hatters, Cap and Millinery Workers. Several letters in 1938-1939 concern the National Women's Committee for a Leon Blum Colony in Palestine, of which Schneiderman was chair.
    - Correspondence, 1915-1917 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1918-1922 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1924, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1929-1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1933-1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 11, Box Shared Tamiment 040)
    - Correspondence, 1943-1947 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1951, 1956-1957, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Subseries C: Correspondence, Undated. (Reel 7099/113: Frames 786-914)
    The undated letters are arranged in a rough chronological sequence as suggested by the content. Included area few letters from WTUL figures, including Mary Dreier, Mabel Gillespie, and Melinda Scott. (Undated items for a particular year are included with the correspondence for that year, either before or after the dated items.)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence not Microfilmed: Letter from Louis Friedland, Educational Director, ILGWU, to Jacob Hillquit (2/14/1920); Letter from Olga Long (Finnish Women's Cooperative Home, "Dear Comrade," [1912?], 1912, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 15A)
- Series II: Special Topics. (Reel 7099/114, Part 1: Frames 1-782)
  (Reel 2, Part 1: Frames 1-782)
  - Subseries A: Women's Trade Union League.
    Women's Trade Union League (Reel 2, Part 1: Frames 1-186): The items are divided, somewhat haphazardly, into three groups: general material (frames 1-60), speeches and articles by Rose Schneiderman (frames 63-157), and miscellaneous (frames 158-186). Included in the first group are: typed copies of reports in the Chicago Union Labor Advocate of the founding meetings of the National WTUL in 1903 (by one of the participants, Ellen Lindstrom), of the national "convention" of 1907 (actually a small conference held during the annual convention of the American Federation of Labor), and of early meetings of the Chicago and Boston branches; a typed report by Rose Schneiderman of her work as organizer for the New York WTUL in 1908-1909; minutes of a meeting of the Law Enforcement Committee of the New York WTUL in 1913; and the script of the League's surprise party for Schneiderman in 1943. In the second group (speeches and articles), each ofthe first two speeches lacks page 1. In a speech or article at the end of the group Schneiderman looks back over the fifty-year history of the New York WTUL after its decision to disband.
    - WTUL Training School, 1913-1938 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - WTUL Clippings and Articles, 1904-1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - WTUL Resolutions and Minutes, Members of Executive Committee, 1903-1919 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - WTUL Executive Board Meeting Minutes, Letters and Finances, 1911-1950 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - WTUL Executive Board Meeting Minutes, 1930-1938 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - WTUL Executive Board Meeting Minutes, 1939; 1943 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - WTUL Speeches, Schneiderman, 1906-1955 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - WTUL Miscellaneous Reports, etc., 1908-1933 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - WTUL: Luncheon, 1949; 25th Anniversary Dinner, 1943, 1943-1949 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - WTUL: Catalogs of Exhibits, 1935-1951 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Subseries B: Woman Suffrage.
    Woman Suffrage (Reel 2, Part 1: Frames 187-233): Includes two speeches, presumably by Rose Schneiderman, given at a "suffrage school" in Washington, DC, in 1913.
    - Woman's Suffrage, 1913-1916 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Woman's Suffrage (not microfilmed): Flier for a Series of Public Speaking Engagements by Schneiderman, undated (Box 2, Folder 11A)
  - Subseries C: First International Congress of Working Women.
    First International Congress of Working Women (Reel 2, Part 1: Frames 234-243): Contains several documents relating to the WTUL's efforts to convene this Congress, held in Washington DC in October 1919.
    - First International Congress of Working Women, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Subseries D: International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.
    International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (Reel 2, Part 1: Frames 244-279): Consists largely of minutes of the Waist Makers Conference in New York City, 1910-11, of which Schneiderman was secretary.
    - International Ladies' Garment Workers Union, 1910-1911 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Subseries E: New York State Department of Labor. Industrial Board. Committee on Sanitation and Comfort.
    New York State Department of Labor. Industrial Board. Committee on Sanitation and Comfort (Reel 2, Part 1: Frames 280-450): Includes letters to Schneiderman and other members from the committee's head, Pauline Goldmark, together with reports, drafts of sanitary regulations, and related papers. (See also letters on Reel 1, frames 356 and 363.)
    - New York State Department of Labor. Industrial Board. Committee on Sanitation and Comfort, 1913-1914 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Subseries F: Labor Advisory Board, National Recovery Administration.
    Labor Advisory Board, National Recovery Administration (Reel 2, Part 1: Frames 451-661): ALoosely organized, includes three Schneiderman speeches, some correspondence, various internal memoranda and minutes, and an unsigned typescript history of the board.
    - Draft History of the Board, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Statements, Speeched, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Memorandum and Minutes, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Subseries G: Miscellaneous Speeches and Broadcasts by Rose Schneiderman.
    Miscellaneous Speeches and Broadcasts by Rose Schneiderman (Reel 2, Part 1: Frames 662-782): Contains typsecripts of speeches and radio broadcasts given from 1935-1947.
    - Speeches and Broadcasts, 1935-1946, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Speeches during/re: World War II, 1943-1947 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Series III: Biographical and Personal. (Reel 7099/114, Part 2: Frames 1-28)
  - Subseries A: Rose Schneiderman.
    (Reel 2, Part 2: Frames 1-28): Includes occasional pages of typed recollections by Rose Schneiderman, probably related to the writing of her autobiography.
    - Biographical: Recollections by Schneiderman and others re: Schneiderman, 1943, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Songs and Poems, 1943, 1946, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Vacation in Italy, 1923, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Subseries B: Friends and Associates.
    (Reel 2, Part 2: Frames 29-49): Includes a typed biographical sketch of Elisabeth Christman by Pauline Newman and two items on Mary N. Winslow.
    - Biographies, Others, 1925, 1939, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Robins, Margaret Dreier, 1945, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor: Dinner in Honor of, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor & Franklin: Invitations, 1937, 1941, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor & Franklin: Miscellaneous, 1933, 1943-1945, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Subseries C: Miscellaneous.
    (Reel 2, Part 2: Frames 50-97): The miscellaneous section includes Schneiderman's commission from Governor Alfred E. Smith to represent New York State at a child labor conforence in 1924.
    - "All for One" typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Awards and Citations, 1924-1965 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Awards and Citations (Oversize), 1948-1961 (Box Tamiment Shared MSXOS002, Folder 1)
    - Incomplete {untitled} Typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Leon Blum Colony in Palestine, 1938, 1939, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1924-1944 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Puerto Rico: Notes on Industrial Conditions, 1934, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Visit WAAC Training Center, ca. 1942-1945 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series IV: Newspaper Clippings. (Reel 7099/114, Part 2: Frames 98-232)
  (Reel 2, Part 2: Frames 98-232)
  - Clippings, folder 1 of 3, 1912-1972 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, 1924-1972 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
- Series V: Pauline Newman Letters. (Not microfilmed)
  Items not microfilmed
  Existence and Location of Copies
  Photocopies of contents of Box 5 exist in Box 6 located at the Tamiment Library and are available for researcher use.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original materials are fragile. Researchers must use photocopies in box 6.
  - Letters (Originals), 1910-1912 (Box 5, Folder 3-5)
  - Letters (Photocopies), 1910-1912 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)